# **Ben Barten**

Berlin, Germany | +491732858724 | contact@benbarten.com linkedin.com/in/ben-barten | github.com/benbarten | benbarten.com

#### PROFESSIONAL SUMMARY

Self-taught, polyglot and product-minded software engineer with 7+ years of professional experience specializing in backend development. Successfully, architected and built software in various domains for start-ups, scale-ups and established enterprises. Demonstrated the ability to decide when to prioritize getting stuff done and when to take a step back to focus on scalability and stability.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

#### Technical Lead, Semrush

July 2023 - now

- Leading the data management team which is responsible for the data infrastructure of the Enterprise platform
- Building a petabyte-scale data lake on top of Google BigQuery
- Mentored junior engineers who evolved into senior engineers
- Planned and executed a 4-month migration process to rebuild the database design of the data lake with 0 impact on customers
- Reduced the data gathering error rate of our ETL jobs by 90%
- 50+ technical and behavioral interviews of backend engineers
- The Enterprise platform went from 0 to Xm ARR within 18 months

## Senior Software Engineer, Semrush

August 2022 - June 2023

- Setup the infrastructure for the Enterprise platform using Kubernetes, Docker, Helm, Gitlab CI and Google Cloud Platform (GCP)
- Wrote the first line of code of the Enterprise platform's backend
- Built a role-based-access-control (RBAC) system to manage workspaces and projects for customers in Go
- Built a Go SQL compiler for a low-code data query builder to allow our Solution Architects to build custom-tailored dashboards within hours without engineering involvement
- Led the backend chapter to foster cross-team collaboration and knowledge sharing within the Enterprise unit

#### **Backend Software Engineer, Fraugster**

March 2021 - July 2022

- Built and maintained the production real-time API for transaction scoring in Go
- Developed a microservice-based low latency data processing pipeline with each transaction being scored in less than 15ms (95th percentile) in Go
- Extracted parts of a monolithic system into a microservice to enable horizontal scaling and ensure 99.99% uptime
- Supported in building a deployment pipeline for the ML team to run deploy ML models with Gitlab CI and kubernetes
- Decoupled the transaction API from the data processing pipeline for easier testing and increased test coverage from 20% to 65%

## Lead Software Engineer, fino

Dec 2019 - February 2021

- Led a team of 3 backend developers including regular 1:1s and performance feedbacks
- Built a company-wide API platform for banks and fintech companies to open up B2B revenue streams in the Banking-as-a-Service domain
- Implemented an API-first mindset within the company including API design standards and a developer portal
- Utilized domain driven design (DDD) techniques to compose a unified API layer on top of our microservice architecture in Go

#### Software Engineer, fino

Aug 2017 - November 2019

- Part of the data analysis team developing financial account analysis algorithms for some of Germany's largest banks in Java and Python
- Built a custom rule engine for transaction classification reducing 80% of manual efforts of developers supporting in transaction classification

- Built a account balance forecasting algorithm to predict monthly spending of personal bank accounts in Python
- Leveraged Docker to containerize above mentioned algorithms and deploy them with Jenkins
- Developed a backend-for-frontend (BFF) for our web/mobile application "Yoli" to access the account analysis using GraphQL

### **SKILLS**

Languages: Go, Java, Javascript (ES6+), Bash

**Technologies**: Kubernetes, Helm, Docker, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, Google BigQuery, Redis, Apache Kafka, RabbitMQ, REST, gRPC, GCP, AWS, Gitlab CI, Azure DevOps

## **EDUCATION**

Secondary Teaching, English / Physical Education, Universität Kassel Abitur, Oberstufengymnasium Eschwege

October 2013 - October 2017 July 2011

## **PROJECTS**

Technical Lead, Semrush Enterprise (<u>semrush.com/enterprise/seo</u>) Software Engineer, Fraugster (<u>fraugster.com</u>) Lead Software Engineer, finoOS (<u>os.fino.ai</u>) currently March 2021 - July 2022 December 2019 - February 2021

### **CERTIFICATIONS**

• Stanford Online - Coursera - Machine Learning

DesignCourse.com - CSS Course

April 2022 October 2023